money patterns decoded
every April over 100 million Americans check one number
and almost all of them celebrate
what if that Celebration is the problem
in 2024 the average federal tax refund hit $3,167
an all time record high
74% of all tax filers received one
most of them called it a win
almost none of them asked the right question about it
but here's what's actually happening
and once you see it you can't unsee it
but here's what almost nobody knows about that refund
including the people who just deposited one
the average refund in 2010 was $1,952
by 2024 it was 3,167
that's a 62% increase in 14 years
US wages grew 47% over the same period
the refund is growing
faster than the income it came from
every year Nerdwallet surveys filers
on what they plan to do with the money
37% say they'll pay bills
32% say they'll save it
21% say they'll make a big purchase
Only 11% say they'll invest it
but that refund money wasn't sitting somewhere
waiting for you it was working
just not for you
to understand why you need to go back to 1943
to understand why your money works this way
you need to go back to 1943
and an emergency decision
that was never meant to become permanent
before 1940
just 4% of Americans paid federal income tax
tax was something paid by the wealthy once a year
in a lump sum every March
then the war changed everything
the US government needed to fund a global war
immediately not at year end
but right now every paycheck
a young economist named Milton Friedman
was part of the team at the Treasury Department
that designed the solution
paycheck withholding
instead of paying your taxes at year end
your employer
would take the money before it ever reached your hands
the current Tax Payment Act was signed in 1943
written explicitly as a wartime emergency measure
by 1945 74% of Americans were paying federal income tax
up from 4% in just five years
the system was so effective at collecting money fast
that no one ever dismantled it
eighty three years later
it's still running exactly as designed
the economist who helped build it
later wrote that
prepayment
changed how citizens perceived their tax burden
that it had consequences no one had fully anticipated
but what does the design actually do to your money
so let's trace your money
from the first paycheck of January
to the day you get it back
because something interesting happens to it in between
the IRS withholds between 15
and 22% of your gross wages
before you see a cent
that money doesn't sit in a box with your name on it
it flows into the US Treasury's General Fund
and it finances daily government operations
in 2023
the US collected $4.7 trillion in federal tax revenue
eighty four percent of it came from payroll taxes
and individual withholding combined that same year
$334 billion was returned to filers as refunds
money that had been withheld in excess
the government held $334 billion of over withheld money
for an average of around six months
in 2023 the federal funds rate was 5.3%
that float represented approximately $8.9 billion
in interest value to the government
that figure is a conservative estimate
334 billion at 5.3% over roughly half a year
and the interest you
received on your over withheld money
zero
under federal law unless the IRS holds your refund
more than 45 days past the filing deadline
it owes you nothing
but here's where it gets personal
now let's price what that $264 a month
your money could actually be doing
$3,167 divided across 12 months is $264 a month
that's not a windfall that's a monthly decision
made automatically
to hand that amount to the government
instead of directing it yourself
let's say you're 25 years old and starting today
you redirect that $264 into an index fund
averaging 7% annual returns
after five years
seventeen thousand four hundred and fifty three dollars
after 10 years 45,604
after 20 years $163,174 after 30 years $321,207
you contributed 95,000 of your own dollars
over those 30 years
the remaining $226,000 came from compound growth alone
and if investing isn't where you are right now
that same 264 dollars applied monthly
to a 5 thousand dollar credit card balance
at 22.8%
APR saves you 662 dollars in interest this year
but the compound
table is not even the most important part of this story
and here's the part most tax videos skip
the refund is just one example of this
there are at least three others
running in your financial life
right now the mechanism is the same every time
the system produces a feeling of getting something
while the underlying math runs the other direction
credit card rewards
US card holders
received $52.6 billion in rewards in 2022
That same year
they paid $108 billion in credit card interest
roughly $2 in interest for every dollar in rewards
loyalty programs
30% of all earned points expire before they're redeemed
estimated unredeemed US loyalty points
at any given time $360 billion
and employer 401k matching
67% of employees
don't fully understand how to maximize their match
guaranteed returns left on the table
in every case the experience feels like winning
the math doesn't agree
but the US isn't alone in having income tax
what makes it unusual
is the system it built around collecting it
the US isn't the only country with income tax
but it might be the only major one
that turns the repayment into an annual event
you have to file for yourself
in Japan 95% of salary workers never file a tax return
their employer withholds and reconciles taxes
automatically the government does the math
the citizen does nothing in the United Kingdom
32.7 million workers are covered by P a
y E
pay as you earn no annual filing required
in Denmark over
90% of citizens receive a pre completed return
that requires no action at all
in Australia 87% of individual tax returns
are pre populated with employer
and bank data by the government
approximately 30 nations
have implemented automatic reconciliation
or pre filled return systems
the US is the only major OECD economy that has not
Americans spend
6.5 billion hours per year on federal tax compliance
the tax preparation industry
Turbotax HR Block Accountants
generates $15.4 billion annually from that requirement
that is not a technical limitation
that is a policy decision
and the reason most people never question any of this
is the same reason the refund still feels good
even after you understand what it is
so why does it still feel good
that's not an accident
the belief a tax refund is bonus money
extra separate from your regular income
the mechanism it is your income collected in excess
held for four months returned without interest
the feeling of different money
has a name in behavioral economics
mental accounting
Richard Thaler formally described it in 1985
the theory that the same dollar feels different
depending on how it arrives
loss aversion documented by Kahneman and Tversky
shows that people work
roughly twice as hard to avoid a loss
as to achieve an equivalent gain
the withholding system converts
what should feel like a monthly reduction
into a once a year win
studies suggest 60 to 70% of refund recipients
describe the check as a bonus
even people who intellectually
know it is their own money
the economist who helped design this system wrote that
prepayment
changed how citizens perceived the cost of government
it made the tax burden feel less visible
that was not a flaw in the design
that was the system working exactly as intended
you were never irrational
you were responding to a stimulus
engineered to produce exactly that response
but knowing this changes what you can do about it
the good news is this is fixable
and it takes less than 10 minutes
one form one free government tool
four steps step 1
get your most recent pay stub
step 2 go to IRS dot gov slash w four app
the IRS Tax Withholding Estimator free
no login required
step 3 update step 4
c on your W4 form that's the specific line that
controls additional withholding
step 4
submit the updated W4 to your HR or payroll department
it takes effect within one to two pay periods
the goal is not a zero refund
and definitely not to owe money at filing time
owing more than $1,000 at filing
can trigger under withholding penalties
the target is a refund of 200 to 500 dollars
what tax professionals call the wash zone
small enough
that the government isn't holding thousands of yours
large enough to confirm you haven't underwithheld
and that $264 a month
that comes back into your paycheck
put it in a high yield savings account at roughly 4.9%
and it earns you $155 this year
before you touch it or put it toward debt
or your emergency fund or your index fund
the point isn't the specific use
the point is that it's working for you
not the government you were never getting a gift
you were getting your own money back late
without interest
after it helped finance the operations of a government
you already pay taxes to
the goal was never the refund
it was the money $264 a month
working for you the way it was always supposed to
if this is the kind of pattern you want to understand
before it runs in the background of your finances
this channel posts every Saturday
next week credit card rewards
who they're actually designed to benefit
and why the math almost never works
the way the ads say it does money patterns decoded